{"tossups": [{"question": "Ibn Battuta chose to spend the night on his ship rather than sleep in the city of Zayla in this modern country, as the stench of fish and camel blood was too much to bear. Cinnamon was brought to the city of Mosylon in this modern country before being transported to the Roman Empire. Yusuf al-Kawneyn was an Islamic scholar from this modern country who is credited with bringing Islam to the Maldives. The Ottomans allied with the (*) Ajuran Sultanate based in this modern country to curtail Portuguese influence in the western Indian Ocean. This modern country is the [emphasize] southernmost candidate for the location of the land of Punt referenced in ancient Egyptian sources. For 10 points, identify this modern country whose capital of Mogadishu rose to prominence in the Medieval period.", "answer": "Somalia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Somalia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Somalia", "Somalia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Notorious con man Monroe Edwards smuggled slaves from this modern country into the Republic of Texas by claiming that they were indentured servants with 99-year contracts. Ambrosio Jos\u00e9 Gonzales, a citizen of this modern country, supported American interests there and served as a general in the Confederate Army. The cessation of US support in a rebellion in this modern country was promoted by Manuel Urrutia Lle\u00f3. In what many locals thought was a coverup, (*)\u00a0 Charles Magoon ordered the removal of the wreckage of a ship from the harbor of this modern country\u2019s capital. This modern country\u2019s current flag was designed in part by a man who tried to forcibly make it join the US, Narciso L\u00f3pez. For 10 points, name this country that lies only about 100 miles south of Florida with a capital of Havana.", "answer": "Republic of Cuba", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Republic of Cuba</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Republic of Cuba", "Republic of Cuba"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The southern reaches of this mountain range has been given the contested appellation of the \u201cCountry of Towns\u201d for the several fortified Bronze Age settlements found in the area. The existence of the Classical \u201cRiphean Mountains\u201d was validated by the writings of Sigismund von Herberstein on this mountain range. A steel-producing town in this mountain range was modeled after Gary, Indiana. A route crossing this mountain range using a series of rivers and portages began at the town of Cherdyn until it was eventually supplanted by a path blazed by (*) Artemy Babinov. The Stroganov family funded a military expedition east of this mountain range, leading to Yermak\u2019s conquest of the Khanate of Sibir. For 10 points, name this Russian mountain range, the conventional northern division between Europe and Asia.", "answer": "Ural Mountains", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ural</u></b> Mountains", "acceptable": ["Ural Mountains", "Ural"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A 1932 assassination attempt on a holder of this position also targeted Charlie Chaplin, but he was at an event with that holder of this position\u2019s son when the attempt happened. A holder of this position committed suicide after refusing to cooperate with Bonner Feller\u2019s \u201cOperation Blacklist\u201d and had earlier arranged secret negotiations with Joseph Grew. That holder of this position led the \u201cNew Order Movement\u201d and attempted to institute one-party rule through his (*) Imperial Aid Association. Earlier, one of these people were assassinated in the May 15 incident, and many of those assassins had earlier been associated with the League of Blood. Members of the \u201cRighteous Army\u201d assassinated two former holders of this position in the February 26 incident. A holder of this position resigned after the fall of Saipan and was hanged in 1948 after being found guilty of war crimes by the International Military Tribunal for the Far East. For 10 points, name this position which was once held by Hideki Tojo.\u00a0", "answer": "Prime Minister of Japan (accept Japanese Prime Minister)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Prime Minister of Japan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Prime Minister of Japan", "Prime Minister of Japan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Japanese Prime Minister"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable The act of amending this document was called \u201cadding to the rafters\u201d. This document gives women the right to confirm or deny the inheritance of certain political offices, symbolized with their control over strings of shells. This document permits the occasional granting of an advisory office to worthy people interested in governance; such people were likened to newly-sprung pine trees. Four joined white squares with a white pine in the middle represents the unity this document codified and was originally depicted on a belt made of (*) wampum. Known as the Great Law of Peace, this document was the culmination of the work of the Peacemaker and granted the centrally-located Onondaga the title \u201cKeepers of the Fire\u201d. For 10 points, identify this document, which directed the governance of a confederation of Native American tribes in upstate New York.", "answer": "Great Law of Peace of the Iroquois League (accept descriptive answers along the lines of the Iroquois constitution; accept Gayanashagowa; accept Haudenosaunee in place of \u201cIroquois\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Great Law of Peace of the Iroquois League</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Great Law of Peace of the Iroquois League", "Great Law of Peace of the Iroquois League"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept descriptive answers along the lines of the Iroquois constitution; accept Gayanashagowa; accept Haudenosaunee in place of \u201cIroquois\u201d"}, {"question": "Immense Nazi demands of wine from this region led to one of its major producers walling up reserves of its 1928 vintage, a well-known favorite of Winston Churchill. Frustrated with the onset of the Phylloxera epidemic and the importation of grapes from other regions, wine producers in this region rioted in 1911, burning much of the town of A\u00ff (ah-EE). The founder of a famous wine producer in this region served as mayor of Paris when it was liberated from Nazi rule. Breaking from the trend in the 19th century for wines from this region to be sweet, producer (*) Perrier-Jou\u00ebt produced a dry wine that critics called brut (\u201cbrute\u201d) for its perceived severity. Though he strove to remove the best-known quality of wines from this region, they grew in quality as innovations in pruning, harvesting, and pressing were pioneered by Dom P\u00e9rignon. For 10 points, name this French region that has become synonymous with sparkling wine.", "answer": "Champagne", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Champagne</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Champagne", "Champagne"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "From 1453 on, the Ghisolfi family ruled the Taman Peninsula on behalf of an institution in this industry. A medieval writer connected the city of Cahors to Sodom due to its heavy engagement in this industry. After the condemnation of commendas, the use of a contractum trinius could be used to circumvent restrictions on this industry. Lillian Randall suggested that the Lombards were depicted as snails in medieval manuscripts for participating in this industry. Unfavorable business forced by the English monarchy and mismanagement by (*) Tommaso Portinari were factors in the decline of the London and Bruges branches of an institution in this industry. Many Jews were employed in this industry because of Biblical prohibitions of usury. For 10 points, identify this industry whose modern form was developed by the likes of the Medici\u2019s in late medieval and Renaissance Italy.", "answer": "banking (accept moneylending or finance)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>banking</u></b>", "acceptable": ["banking", "banking"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept moneylending or finance"}, {"question": "Shortly after abandoning Christianity, a man of this ethnic group was unharmed after being locked in a cage with a tiger for preaching the Ayyavazhi religion he founded. A temple built by this people was legendarily rebuilt at the urging of Gangadevi, who chronicled the overthrow of a Muslim power established by Jalauddin Ahsan Khan by her husband Kumara Kampana. An author of this people deified their language in one poem, claiming that it toured its earthly domains through the rulers of three dynasties of this people known as the m\u016bv\u0113ntar, or (*) \u201cthree crowned kings\u201d. The writings of the Nayanars and the Alvars, poet-saints of this people, led to the creation of the bhakti movement. The folklore of this people claims that three meetings of poets resulted in their earliest sangam literature. The ancient Meenakshi Temple lies at the center of this people\u2019s cultural center of Madurai. For 10 points, identify this people whose name precedes \u201cNadu\u201d in the name of a South Indian state.", "answer": "Tamil people (prompt on \u201cDravidians\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tamil</u></b> people", "acceptable": ["Tamil people", "Tamil"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \u201cDravidians\u201d"}, {"question": "Two mountains called the \u201cBreasts of the North\u201d were divinely brought closer together so that this ruler could more easily fortify the pass between them. After falling behind during a campaign to assist an aging friend, this ruler stole fire from the camp of the opposing Arabians to raise his soldiers\u2019 spirits. Because they had no chalk, a city founded by this man was supposedly laid out using barley, which was quickly eaten by birds, portending the prosperity of the city. The Qur\u2019anic story of (*) Dhul-Qarnayn (thool-\u201ccar-nine\u201d) constructing a wall to protect against Gog and Magog is believed to have arisen from mythologized accounts of this ruler. This\u00a0 ruler was supposedly born after the womb of his mother Olympias was struck by a lightning bolt from Zeus. According to Plutarch, this man dreamed of a satyr during a siege, which his seers deemed meant \u201csa Tyros\u201d, or \u201cTyre is yours\u201d. For 10 points, name this Macedonian ruler who conquered the Achaemenid Empire.", "answer": "Alexander the Great (accept Alexander III of Macedon)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Alexander the Great</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Alexander the Great", "Alexander the Great"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Alexander III of Macedon"}, {"question": "An expedition sent out by a leader of this name apocryphally found a land whose residents\u2019 ages changed based on how far up a certain hill they stood. That ruler of this name was supposedly conceived when a princess swallowed a jewel shot into her compound on an arrow by his father. Jacinto Canek (ha-SEEN-toe kah-NAKE) styled himself a \u201clittle\u201d ruler of this name during his 1761 rebellion. The most famous account of the death of a ruler of this name claims that he was killed by (*) stones thrown by his subjects after trying to convince them to make peace with an invading force. Depictions of a god with black skin and the late date, and likely biased nature, of existing accounts make it unlikely that a ruler of this name perceived a Spanish hidalgo as a returning Queztalcoatl. For 10 points, what is this name held by the ruler of the Aztecs upon Cort\u00e9s\u2019 arrival in Mexico?", "answer": "Moctezuma (accept Montezuma, Moteuczoma, Motecuhzoma, Mot\u0113ucz\u014dmah, Muteczuma, Hu\u0113huemot\u0113ucz\u014dma)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Moctezuma</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Moctezuma", "Moctezuma"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Montezuma, Moteuczoma, Motecuhzoma, Mot\u0113ucz\u014dmah, Muteczuma, Hu\u0113huemot\u0113ucz\u014dma"}, {"question": "Specific term required Quentin Skradec likened William McGuffey to Minerva in the \u201cpantheon of American capitalism and [this idea]\u201d. Pope Leo XIII wrote the letter Testem benevolentiae nostrae in response to the growth of this idea in the Catholic Church in America. Louis Henkin wrote that this idea promoted a \u201cflying buttress mentality\u201d that was attached to, but did not support, human rights. This idea was called a \u201cheresy\u201d for denying the universality of Marxist history by (*) Joseph Stalin. Louis Hartz argued that this idea developed because the US did not have feudalism. Though not the origin of the common name for this idea, John Winthrop expressed it through calling the Massachusetts Bay Colony a \u201ccity upon a hill\u201d. For 10 points, what is this idea that America has a unique and privileged moral and diplomatic position on the world stage?", "answer": "American exceptionalism", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "American <b><u>exceptionalism</u></b>", "acceptable": ["American exceptionalism", "exceptionalism"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Though not directly a part of this agreement, Russian interests were considered by it due to the findings of the De Bunsen Committee. Erle Richards\u2019 \u201cP-memo\u201d advocated for annulling this agreement, in line with the policies laid out in the most famous correspondence of Henry McMahon. One party to this agreement issued the Bassett Letter to reassure an ally of their territorial aspirations after this agreement was made public in the newspapers Pravda and Izvestia; that ally was (*) Hussein bin Ali. The ideas put forward in this agreement were furthered at the San Remo Conference, where it was decided that three Class \u201cA\u201d territories would be given to the involved parties. Widely blamed for the political instability of the Middle East during the last century, for 10 points, what was this 1916 agreement in which the UK and France planned the partition of the Ottoman Empire following WWI?", "answer": "Sykes-Picot Agreement", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sykes-Picot</u></b> Agreement", "acceptable": ["Sykes-Picot Agreement", "Sykes-Picot"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A turn of the twentieth century nationalist movement composed of people of this ethnic group described them as the \u201cchildren of the three zhuz\u201d. Girei and Zhanibek founded and co-ruled a state named after this ethnic group, and later toppled their former Shaybanid master Abu\u2019l-Khair Khan. This ethnic group\u2019s traditional law system, or adat, was considered in the legal reforms of Mikhail Speransky. The Alash Autonomy was a short-lived state formed by members of this ethnic group governed from (*) Semey until conquered in 1920 by the Red Army. Often contested with Russia, the \u201cInner Side\u201d was the name this ethnic group gave to the land west of the Ural River. For 10 points, what is this ethnic group, whose namesake country recently renamed its planned capital city of Astana to Nursultan?", "answer": "Kazakhs", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kazakhs</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kazakhs", "Kazakhs"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Anthropologist Peter Gow has critiqued the tendency of recent historiography of these processes to label the concept of duthchas (TU-khas)*, held by those affected, as \u201calmost untranslatable\u201d. Patrick Sellar was acquitted of homicide for the death of a woman caused by the arson he committed to further these processes. These processes destroyed the power of tacksmen. These processes coincided with a decline in the traditional famine occupation of kelp harvesting. These processes were legally outlawed by the (*) Crofters\u2019 Act of 1886. In a reaction against these processes, residents of Strathrusdale drove 6,000 livestock off their land in 1792, the \u201cYear of the Sheep\u201d. For 10 points, what were these evictions of people from the northern portion of Britain throughout the 18th and 19th centuries, largely to allow for the expansion of sheep grazing?", "answer": "Highland Clearances (prompt on \u201cenclosure\u201d with \u201cOf which region?\u201d, prompt again if given \u201cScotland\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Highland Clearances</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Highland Clearances", "Highland Clearances"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \u201cenclosure\u201d with \u201cOf which region?\u201d, prompt again if given \u201cScotland\u201d"}, {"question": "Finding the \u201cKingdom of Beach\u201d was a goal of a man known for exploring this modern country, who is now the namesake of a body of water to the east of this country sometimes called the Ditch. Peter M\u00fchlh\u00e4usler has proposed that the word for \u201cturtle\u201d in languages like Ngarluma and Karriera is evidence for Portuguese sailors being the first Europeans to reach this modern country. The first confirmed European contact with this country was made by the crew of the Duyfken (dayf-ken). Early European settlement in the west of this modern country centered around the (*) Swan River Colony. William Landsborough crossed this country from north to south in an attempt to find traces of an earlier expedition traveling the other way led by Burke and Wills. This modern country was first circumnavigated by Matthew Flinders. For 10 points, what is this country, which takes its name from the Latin for \u201csouth\u201d?", "answer": "Commonwealth of Australia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Commonwealth of Australia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Commonwealth of Australia", "Commonwealth of Australia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A leader of this state won the Battle of Mari and ravaged the cities of Mamistra, Adana, and Tarsus in Cilician Armenia. While serving this dynasty, Ibn Khaldun held a historic series of meetings with Tamurlane outside Damascus. Barquq took control of this state after a period of 40 years of nominal rule by the descendants of Al-Nasir Muhammad. While serving as a general for [emphasize] another state, a future leader of this state captured a monarch who was ransomed for 400,000 dinars following the Battle of (*) Al Mansurah. This state is broken by Western historians into \u201cBa\u1e25r\u012b\" and \"Burj\u012b\" periods, while historians in the Muslim world name those periods the \u201cCircassian\u201d and \u201cTurkish\u201d periods, respectively. This state\u2019s leaders included Qutuz and Baibars, who won against Kitbuqa and the Ilkhanate at Ayn Jalut. For 10 points, name this Egyptian state which succeeded the Ayyubids, named after an Arabic designation for slaves.", "answer": "Mamluk Sultanate", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mamluk Sultanate</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Mamluk Sultanate", "Mamluk Sultanate"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "During the height of Athenian power in the 5th century BC, obstructing the import of this commodity was punishable by death. Hadrian recruited the Vulpes, a secret service, from men who worked with this commodity. In Athens, sitones were specialized traders in this commodity, which was regulated by sitophylakes. By the advent of the latifundia owned by senators, this commodity had become unprofitable to source from Italy, which relied on imports instead. Puclher abolished a form of distribution of this commodity in the late Roman Republic called the (*) frumentatio. Around a third of the early Roman Empire state\u2019s revenues were spent on providing a product made with this commodity to its citizens, called the annona. Because it dedicated most of its arable land to growing olives, ancient Athens heavily relied on large amounts of this commodity imported from southern Russia, Ukraine, and Pontus. For 10 points, identify this staple crop grown on the Nile River that, along with wine and olives, made up the majority of the Roman diet.", "answer": "wheat (accept grain; prompt on \u201cbread\u201d or \u201cflour\u201d by asking what it was made with)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>wheat</u></b>", "acceptable": ["wheat", "wheat"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept grain; prompt on \u201cbread\u201d or \u201cflour\u201d by asking what it was made with"}, {"question": "Carl Peters forced villagers in this colony to meet cotton-growing quotas, and Chief Mkwawa of the Hehe people resisted this colony\u2019s expansion. A rebellion in this colony was led by a medium named Bokero and was named after the mixture of water, castor oil and bullets given by Bokero to his followers to protect against bullets. The Abushiri revolt was suppressed in this colony, which was ceded land that belonged to Khalifah bin Said. During a battle in this colony, units of the Indian Expeditionary Force under the command of Arthur Aitken were attacked by (*) bees during the Battle of Tanga, and this colony had earlier seen the Maji-Maji rebellion. General Lettow-Vorbeck led Askari troops in a guerilla campaign in this colony during World War I, after which it was partitioned by Portugal, Belgium and Britain. For 10 points, name this German colony whose land area included present-day Burundi, Rwanda, and mainland Tanzania.", "answer": "German East Africa (accept just East Africa after \u201cGerman colony\u201d is read; prompt on \u201cTanganyika\u201d; do not accept or prompt on \u201cGerman South-West Africa\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>German East Africa</u></b>", "acceptable": ["German East Africa", "German East Africa"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept just East Africa after \u201cGerman colony\u201d is read; prompt on \u201cTanganyika\u201d; do not accept or prompt on \u201cGerman South-West Africa\u201d"}, {"question": "In the Supreme Court Case Field v. Clark, the provisions of this tariff were found to not violate the nondelegation doctrine. Douglas Irwin has studied how this tariff \u201cpromoted infant industries\u201d such as the tinplate industry. This tariff\u2019s \u201creciprocity provision\u201d permitted the president to match foreign rate hikes on industries such as coffee and tea. The architect of this tariff, known as the \u201cNapoleon of Protection\u201d, had earlier opposed the election of Joseph (*) Foraker to a third term as governor. This tariff eliminated the preferential status given to sugar imported from Hawaii. The Wilson-Gorman Tariff adjusted the rates set by this tariff, which raised average import duties to 49%. For 10 points, name this tariff whose namesake architect was president during the Spanish-American War.\u00a0", "answer": "McKinley Tariff", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>McKinley</u></b> Tariff", "acceptable": ["McKinley Tariff", "McKinley"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In both the songs \u201cBuffalo\u201d and \u201cTamale\u201d, Tyler the Creator claims that he\u2019s \u201cback like\u201d this person. The 2020 song \u201cYikes\u201d by Nikki Minaj sparked controversy after supposedly disrespecting this person. A song named after this person led to a long-running trial between this person and LaFace records. That song mentions a woman who tells its artists, \u201cyou only funky as your last cut / You focus on the past your ass'll be a has what,\u201d and has a chorus that begins, \u201cAh ha, hush that fuss\u201d. In a Cyhi the Prynce verse on the Kanye West song \u201cSo Appalled\u201d, this person is paired with Ralph Abernathy. This person titles a 1998 song by (*) OutKast off their album Aquemini. A 2002 CBS television movie about this person\u2019s \u201cstory\u201d features Angela Bassett playing this person. For 10 points, name this civil rights pioneer whose refusal to give up her seat to a white passenger sparked the Montgomery Bus Boycott.\u00a0", "answer": "Rosa Parks", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Rosa <b><u>Parks</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Rosa Parks", "Parks"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}